कृषि -X- _ O
विभाग -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
मिले -X- _ O
जानकारी -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
मुताबिक -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
किसान -X- _ O
मन -X- _ O
ल -X- _ O
’’श्री -X- _ B-Person
पद्धति’’ -X- _ O
से -X- _ O
धान -X- _ O
बोनी -X- _ O
बर -X- _ O
प्रोत्साहन -X- _ O
देहे -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
क्रम -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
अब -X- _ O
तक -X- _ O
540 -X- _ O
हेक्टेयर -X- _ O
क्षेत्र -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
’’श्री -X- _ B-Person
पद्धति’’ -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
धान -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
बोनी -X- _ O
करइया -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

अऊ -X- _ O
’’श्री -X- _ B-Person
पद्धति’’ -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
करे -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
लगभग -X- _ O
दू -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
ढाई -X- _ O
गुना -X- _ O
जादा -X- _ O
उत्पादन -X- _ O
होही। -X- _ O

ए -X- _ O
पद्धति -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
बर -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
विकासखंड -X- _ O
गीदम -X- _ B-Location
अऊ -X- _ O
दंतेवाड़ा -X- _ B-Location
क्षेत्र -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
किसान -X- _ O
मन -X- _ O
से -X- _ O
जादा -X- _ O
रूचि -X- _ O
देखावत -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

’’श्री -X- _ B-Person
पद्धति’’ -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
बोआई -X- _ O
करे -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
पानी -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
कम -X- _ O
जरूरत -X- _ O
परथे -X- _ O
संगेच -X- _ O
ए -X- _ O
पद्धति -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
करे -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
फसल -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
रोग -X- _ O
घलोक -X- _ O
लगे -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
संभावना -X- _ O
घलोक -X- _ O
कम -X- _ O
रहिथे। -X- _ O

अभी -X- _ O
हाल -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
बारिश -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
स्थिति -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
अच्छा -X- _ O
होए -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
चलते -X- _ O
किसान -X- _ O
मन -X- _ O
ल -X- _ O
’’श्री -X- _ B-Person
पद्धति’’ -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
बर -X- _ O
अनुकूल -X- _ O
अवसर -X- _ O
मिले -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

’’श्री -X- _ B-Person
पद्धति’’ -X- _ O
बोआई -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
आन -X- _ O
लाभ -X- _ O
मन -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
कम -X- _ O
बीज -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
जादा -X- _ O
उत्पादन -X- _ O
घलोक -X- _ O
सामिल -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

परंपरागत -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
एक -X- _ O
हेक्टेयर -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
जहां -X- _ O
50 -X- _ B-Quantity
ले -X- _ I-Quantity
60 -X- _ I-Quantity
किलो -X- _ I-Quantity
बीज -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
जरूरत -X- _ O
परथे -X- _ O
, -X- _ O
उहें -X- _ O
’’श्री -X- _ B-Person
पद्धति’’ -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
धान -X- _ B-Materials
के -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
बीज -X- _ O
जरूरत -X- _ O
महज -X- _ O
पांच -X- _ B-Quantity
ले -X- _ I-Quantity
छै -X- _ I-Quantity
किलो -X- _ I-Quantity
के -X- _ O
ही -X- _ O
होथे। -X- _ O

दंतेवाड़ा -X- _ B-Location
: -X- _ O
प्राकृतिक -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
संग -X- _ O
सफलता -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
नवा -X- _ O
कहानी -X- _ O
लिखत -X- _ O
हें -X- _ O
महिला -X- _ O
किसानदंतेवाड़ा -X- _ B-Location
, -X- _ O
03 -X- _ B-Date
मार्च -X- _ I-Date
2024। -X- _ I-Date

प्रकृति -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
गोद -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
बसे -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
दंतेवाड़ा -X- _ B-Location
म -X- _ O
प्राकृतिक -X- _ O
रूप -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
प्रचलन -X- _ O
रहे -X- _ O
हे -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
अंतर्गत -X- _ O
अभी -X- _ O
हाल -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
किसान -X- _ O
मन -X- _ O
छिड़काव -X- _ O
विधि -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
करथें। -X- _ O

मन -X- _ O
ल -X- _ O
वैज्ञानिक -X- _ O
विधि -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
गुण -X- _ O
सिखाए -X- _ O
जात -X- _ O
हे -X- _ O
इही -X- _ O
कड़ी -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
समुदाय -X- _ O
आधारित -X- _ O
संहवनीय -X- _ O
कृषि -X- _ O
उप -X- _ O
योजना -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
जुड़े -X- _ O
03 -X- _ O
विकासखंड -X- _ O
दंतेवाड़ा -X- _ B-Location
गीदम -X- _ B-Location
कुआकोंडा -X- _ B-Location
म -X- _ O
कार्यरत -X- _ O
80 -X- _ B-Count
ले -X- _ O
जादा -X- _ O
कृषि -X- _ O

जिला -X- _ O
मिशन -X- _ O
प्रबंधन -X- _ O
इकाई -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
आजीविका -X- _ B-Person
टीम -X- _ I-Person
ह -X- _ O
बताइस -X- _ O
कि -X- _ O
रासायनिक -X- _ O
खाद -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
उपयोग -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
उपजे -X- _ O
साग -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
सेवन -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
मानव -X- _ O
शरीर -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
बहुत -X- _ O
अकन -X- _ O
दुष्प्रभाव -X- _ O
परथे -X- _ O
काबर -X- _ O
कि -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
दंतेवाड़ा -X- _ B-Location
पूरा -X- _ O
जैविक -X- _ O
जिला -X- _ O
बने -X- _ O
बर -X- _ O
आगू -X- _ O
बढ़त -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

किसान -X- _ O
कुंवर -X- _ B-Person
सिंह -X- _ I-Person
ह -X- _ O
भांटा-पताल -X- _ B-Materials
के -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
साल -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
25 -X- _ B-Money
लाख -X- _ I-Money
रूपिया -X- _ I-Money
के -X- _ O
शुद्ध -X- _ O
मुनाफा -X- _ O
कमाथेजांजगीर -X- _ B-Location
19 -X- _ O
फरवरी -X- _ O
2024। -X- _ O

छत्तीसगढ़ -X- _ B-Organization
शासन -X- _ I-Organization
के -X- _ O
उघानिकी -X- _ B-Organization
विभाग -X- _ I-Organization
के -X- _ O
योजना -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
लाभ -X- _ O
लेके -X- _ O
जांजगीर -X- _ B-Location
चांपा -X- _ I-Location
जिला -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
किसान -X- _ O
उन्नत -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
कोति -X- _ O
आगू -X- _ O
बढ़त -X- _ O
हें। -X- _ O

पामगढ़ -X- _ B-Location
विकास -X- _ O
खंड -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
बारगांव -X- _ B-Location
के -X- _ O
किसान -X- _ O
कुंवर -X- _ B-Person
सिंह -X- _ I-Person
मधुकर -X- _ I-Person
ह -X- _ O
ग्राफ्टेड -X- _ O
बैंगन -X- _ B-Materials
अऊ -X- _ O
टमाटर -X- _ B-Materials
के -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
लगभग -X- _ O
हर -X- _ O
एक -X- _ O
साल -X- _ O
25 -X- _ B-Money
लाख -X- _ I-Money
रूपिया -X- _ I-Money
के -X- _ O
शुद्ध -X- _ O
मुनाफा -X- _ O
कमावत -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

एक -X- _ O
एकड़ -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
खीरा -X- _ B-Materials
के -X- _ O
खेती -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
घलोक -X- _ O
ओ -X- _ O
ल -X- _ O
दू -X- _ B-Money
लाख -X- _ I-Money
के -X- _ O
अकतहा -X- _ O
मुनाफा -X- _ O
हो -X- _ O
जाथे। -X- _ O

वो -X- _ O
ह -X- _ O
उघानिकी -X- _ B-Organization
विभाग -X- _ I-Organization
के -X- _ O
राष्ट्रीय -X- _ O
कृषि -X- _ O
विकास -X- _ O
योजना -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
जुड़े -X- _ O
हे -X- _ O
तब -X- _ O
ले -X- _ O
वोखर -X- _ O
जीवन -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
बदलाव -X- _ O
आना -X- _ O
शुरू -X- _ O
हो -X- _ O
गए -X- _ O
हे -X- _ O
आज -X- _ O
पूरा -X- _ O
प्रदेश -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
ओखर -X- _ O
नाम -X- _ O
प्रगतिशील -X- _ O
किसान -X- _ O
के -X- _ O
रूप -X- _ O
म -X- _ O
जाने -X- _ O
जात -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

वो -X- _ O
ह -X- _ O
खुशी -X- _ O
जाहिर -X- _ O
करत -X- _ O
मुख्यमंत्री -X- _ O
श्री -X- _ O
विष्णु -X- _ B-Person
देव -X- _ I-Person
साय -X- _ I-Person
ल -X- _ O
धन्यवाद -X- _ O
देहे -X- _ O
हे। -X- _ O

